Frederick William Betts Papers
Frederick William Betts Papers
1885-1932
Betts, Frederick William.
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American clergyman. Betts (1858-1932) was the minister of the First Church Universalist, Syracuse, N.Y. Collection includes letters, notes, and sermons of a Universalist minister, also published articles and clippings by Betts and others.
148849
Biographical History
Frederick W. Betts (1858-1932) was born in Winnebago County, Illinois on March 6, 1858. He attended St. Lawrence University from 1884 to 1885, and the next year was ordained a Unitarian Universalist minister in Plymouth, New Hampshire. After several years in Plymouth, Betts moved to Syracuse, New York, where he became minister of the First Church, a position he held until his death. He was also active in civic affairs, serving as president of the Associated Charities of Syracuse (1906-1910), president of the Board of Syracuse Public Library, and as chairman of the Syracuse chapter of the American Red Cross. Betts wrote several books, including A Philosophy and Faith of Universalism, The Abiding Life, and Forty Fruitful Years.
Mr. Betts married the former Mary R. Browning in 1878 and the couple had two children, Welcome A. and C. Fred.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frederick W. Betts Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts and published material. Correspondence contains two letters, one outcoming (Betts to his parishioners) and one incoming (from the Church secretary, written after Betts' death). Manuscripts include letters, notes, and sermons written by Betts. Published material consists of an article by Patterson and MacCauley, newspaper clippings about Betts and others, and a prayer in Betts' memory.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and Printed material are arranged chronologically. Manuscripts are arranged in alphabetical order by type and then chronologically within each type.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Church and clergy; Betts, Frederick William Archives.; Clergy, New York (State), Syracuse.; Clergy as authors.; Sermons, American, 19th century.; Universalists.; Clippings (information artifacts); Letters (correspondence); Sermons.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. C. Betts, 1963.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Lectures, 1902; 1904 (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 1)
  - Sermons
    - 1885-1887, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1888-1895 (March), 8 folders (Box 2)
    - 1895 (April)-1902, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - 1903-1909, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Published material
  - The Fruits of Imperialism, by Patterson and MacCauley, 1902 (Box 5)
  - Clippings
    - About Betts, 1901 (Box 5)
    - About others, 1901-1902 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1904; 1905,; 1916,; undated (Box 5)
  - Prayer, in memory of Betts (Box 5)